### Contact

nabeelahmedawan@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ maliknabeelahmed (LinkedIn)

## Top Skills

Java

MySQL

**JSP** 

## Languages

English (Professional Working)
Urdu (Native or Bilingual)
Hindko (Native or Bilingual)

### Certifications

Spring: Spring Cloud

Cloud Architecture: Core Concepts

### Honors-Awards

Institue Silver Medal

### **Publications**

Job Description Ontology

Detect HTTP Specification Attacks using Ontology

Mapping Natural Language
Questions to SPARQL Queries for
Job Search

A New Approach to Information Extraction in User-Centric E-Recruitment Systems

Extracting Semantic Annotation and their Correlation with Document

# Malik Nabeel Ahmed Awan

Senior Manager - Cyber Security Product Development at CydeaTech

Northern Punjab Rawalpindi, Pakistan

# Summary

Highly motivated information technology professional with over eight(08) years of professional experience in planning, architecture and implementing state of the art technology solutions. I am a quick starter, focused solution-oriented programmer and strong in object-oriented analysis, and design.

# Experience

CydeaTechnologies
Senior Manager - Cybersecurity Product Development
July 2019 - Present
Islamabad

Trillium Information Security Systems
Senior Manager - Cybersecurity Product Development
May 2018 - June 2019 (1 year 2 months)

Northern Punjab Rawalpindi, Pakistan

Contour Software Senior Software Developer April 2018 - April 2018 (1 month)

Lahore, Pakistan

Active Capital IT
Software Solution Architect
March 2015 - March 2018 (3 years 1 month)
Islamabad

- Research, design, and implementation of the linked data model for cultural heritage using Apache CXF, Graph DB, MongoDB, Elastic Search, and PostgreSQL.
- Design and implementation of institutional reporting module using Apache Kafka, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Elastic Search, Amazon S3, Apache CXF and Jasper Reports.

- Design and Implementation of Messaging Queue for uploading and execution of bulk jobs using RabbitMQ.
- Documentation of application flows for scalability analysis.
- Design and implement scalability monitoring using App Dynamics and New Relic.
- Implementation of scripts for deployment of applications on Sagoku platform.
- Working with the team for deployment of production application using Jenkins.
- Working with the team for deployment of production application on Sagoku platform.
- Create and manage pipeline in bit-bucket for application deployment.
- Working with US team for requirement analysis for transforming customer input into a form that development team can understand and work.
- Working with Quality Assurance team in Taiwan for requirement delivery for test scenarios building.
- Working with project management team to plan application design, implementation, deployment, and quality assurance roadmap.
- Helping development team in setting up the local testing environment using Docker and Kubernetecs.
- Helping developing team in application debugging for identification of reported production scale issues.

NUST School of Electrical Engineering & Computer Science 3 years 11 months

Network Administrator March 2015 - November 2015 (9 months) Islamabad

- Virtualization Technologies (VMWare)
- Server Configuration and Setup

Visiting Faculty Member February 2015 - June 2015 (5 months)

Taught course CS 423 - Data Warehouse and Data Mining

#### Team Lead

January 2012 - February 2015 (3 years 2 months) Islamabad

- Involved in application research, design, and architecture.
- Involved in new technology research and product evaluation.

- Design and implantation of HR system using Apache CXF, GATE Framework, Stanford NLP Toolkit, Apache Jena, Lucene and Apache TDB.
- Design and implementation of academic-industry liaison application using Apache CXF, Apache Jena, Apache Lucene and Apache TDB.
- Responsible for project delivery on-time with all agreed upon deliverables/ documentation.
- Working closely with deployment team for smooth product deployment on client site.
- Reporting to top management and project collaborators on projects status.
- Team Management (that included human resource management, task assignment, and reporting, computation resource management) for on-time project completion.

Personforce Consulting Pvt Limited Team Lead (Big Data) October 2013 - January 2014 (4 months) Islamabad

- Design, implement and model linked data for job description skills management.
- Implementation of a job crawler for Fortune 500 companies with job boards on Taleo, bright spyre, indeed, rozee.pk, personforce, monster, job site, total jobs and others.
- Implementation of skills extraction algorithm using GATE Framework and Standford NLP Tool Kit.
- Implementation of an application for sharing skills data using Apache JAX-RS, Apache Lucene, Apache Jena and Apache TDB.

NUST School of Electrical Engineering & Computer Science Senior Software Engineer September 2009 - December 2011 (2 years 4 months)

- Involved in cutting edge state of the art research in semantic security for application layer (L7).
- Implementation of L7 layer security application using MySQL, Apache Jena, Apache TDB, Apache Lucene, Mod Security, Apache2, Apache Tomcat.
- Building deployment box for clients using ESX/ESXi 4.1and VMware vSphere 4.1.
- Setting up testing environment in-house and on the client, premises using ESX/ESXi 4.1and VMware vSphere 4.1.

- Responsible for project documentation that includes technical manuals, deployment manuals, client use manuals and reports for application performance (measuring throughput and detection rates).
- Responsible for team management (that included human resource management, task assignment, and reporting, computation resource management).

NUST School of Electrical Engineering & Computer Science Teaching Assitant / Researcher September 2007 - April 2009 (1 year 8 months)

## Education

National University of Science and Technology

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Information Technology (2019)

National University of Science and Technology Master of Science (MS), Information Technology (2009)

COMSATS Institute of Information Technology Bachelor of Science (BS), Information Technology